hey Frank how you doing bill okay I've
got you on the right line now now I
understand that you've got some big news
that we're going to put on a hollow talk
show especially for students and
Educators in the Florida area but I
imagine that this is something that
could be looked at nationally as well
uh yes I do
uh I just came back from Orlando working
with a group of approximately 13
Communications technology teachers and
we
rewrote the communications technology
Frameworks and uh starting next year in
the state of Florida
calligraphy will become part of the
Florida state standards and
Communications technology now this will
be something that will be practiced in
all the schools then yes it will it will
be offered in uh all the high schools
through the state of Florida
the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet with Daniel
pollography
hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of hello
talk for October 8th
1999 my guest this week is Pearl John
who is a graduate of the Royal College
of Art in London and is currently here
in the states running a program at the
Columbia area Career Center in Columbia
Missouri
and with her program area students have
the opportunity to come in and learn
about lasers and Laser Technology and
she puts them on a path to actually
having a career in these fields as they
continue with their education so we're
going to be talking with pearl in just a
minute and she also has three of her
students from the program that will be
on the show as well telling us a little
bit about how they got involved with the
program and some of the things that they
like about the program and lasers and
holography so it's a great show
I have an announcement before we get
started and this is a very significant
announcement for holography over the
summer I had the opportunity to work
with an educator who came up to my lab
here in Allentown Pennsylvania and he's
from the Florida area or in Florida
and we've been working since mid-summer
on this and I just got a call on Friday
where he told me that this was just
adopted
and here's the announcement
State of Florida is going to
put holography into the curriculum for
all high schools in the state of Florida
beginning with the next school year and
Bill was working
on the technology committee and to make
suggestions on how to rewrite the
standards for the state and we worked
very hard to get information together
that we thought that would be able to
push this over the edge and get this
pushed through and Bill was successful
in doing this and I believe although I'm
not quite certain but I'm close to 100
certain that this is the first time in
the United States that an entire state
has mandatory holography program
throughout the heist all high schools in
the state and
from Florida and were looking for other
states now to follow Florida's lead and
it's a very very exciting time not just
for me personally and for Bill
personally but for education and
education people all across the country
to start looking at this program it's a
program that we put together basically
built on the shoebox holography system
and we just added different things to
that program that ties it in with a
number of different academic areas and
bill will be on the show either next
week or the week after to tell everyone
about how he went about doing this how
he got it pushed through and what the
program's all about so that announcement
is that all high schools in the state of
Florida will now be teaching holography
beginning with the next school year and
they will be required to do so so that's
fantastic news all right let's move on
with my interview with pearl John and
she has three of her students with her
this was recorded a few days ago so I'm
going to tag it on the end here I'm not
going to come back on after the show is
over so I will say thank you for tuning
in and I look forward to having you tune
in as a guest each and every week here
at holotalk as we have new topics and
new guests assault about the field that
we all know and love lasers and
holography so here's Pearl
hello this is Frank de Freitas and I
have Pearl John on the line from the
Columbia area Career Center in Columbia
Missouri Paul how are you I'm very well
thank you from two of my students with
me so I'd like to introduce you too
um
and I'm Michael walk on in the photonics
2 program okay so we have Renee and
Michael with you there
okay Pearl how about if we start off
with you I was wondering if you could
give us a little idea of the type of
work that you're doing out there I
assume these are high school or college
students he's a high school student
Renee is a sophomore Mike is a senior I
teach grades 10 through 12 here we have
a year-long introduction to Laser
Technology Program and
um to 30 years Protonix one and two
which introduces
um students the idea of working as laser
technicians
um the
um the courses or the courses were set
up about three or four years ago now and
um although uh
program then you just saw
your stuff and we've got I've got about
90 students now in intro to laser and
about 20 students from photonics one and
two we cover a huge range of
applications for lasers in
related technology we do things like
make Holograms and work with laser light
shows we do laser light sculpture here
as well as doing a lot of very light
Theory and how lasers work and just a
general overview of the applications
now your background is from the Royal
College of Art
that's correct graduated in 92 and
working very much with the official
artist and I started working in schools
from then on as an artist in Residence
and
did a lot of Education along the way a
bit of teaching and photography too but
I've been here now for almost two years
and I have a few questions here that I'd
like to ask you and these questions are
from a friend of mine who I do work with
on occasion her name is Michelle Roy and
she's a career development facilitator
with the freed lands group here in
Pennsylvania and they're involved with
the career and Workforce Development and
she was very interested in you being on
the show and she'll be tuning in to
listen to this as well but she'd like to
know what kind of career paths for kids
in this program do you have right well
um primarily we're encouraging students
who go into the field of related
technology to work as laser technicians
have we're articulated with a college in
Iowa a few year college in Iowa
which a study Laser Technology and
photonics and they go out and work in a
variety of fields but um as native
technicians 4
for our high school students doing
introduction to Laser Technology who
don't particularly want to go on to
photonics we just want to give them a
general idea of just the the sheer
number of jobs out there that's related
to lasers I mean there's
telecommunications jobs available
working with fiber optic they that pays
very well
um
but creative students yes we want to um
give them the opportunity to do work
with the labor light shows and just do a
it's a general fun course so um there is
a point to it in terms of jobs at the
end of the day for those who want to be
local technicians but generally it's a
very Hands-On practical Arts course
that just offers
give us an idea of different fields that
they can go into you know also things
like there's the medical uses of lasers
where people have tattoos and
to remove so there's also
well there's a whole range of
what this latest lighter to learn about
another question that she sent in is
what kinds of students tend to be
interested in this program and those
that are good at it right well we get a
huge range of students and um with
different ranges of academic ability so
um because we're um uh career center we
get a lot of students who um
really do want to work
practical Hands-On courses and they do
better on our courses than they do in
some other more academic areas
so students who haven't in the past been
successful
academic more organic subjects do do
find that they really succeed in nature
technology
as for the students who succeed
they they have to be interested in
problem solving they have to be
interested in working with teams get on
well with each other and really want to
get a job done
so it's a wide range of students it
tends at the most at the moment it tends
to be mostly
boys who are interested and so we are
working very hard to encourage girls
into the field
continue a little bit later about a
Saturday science program that she took
past and that introduced her to the
course but so yeah different range of
abilities we get but
doing holography tends to
um tend to pull in a wide range of
students with wide range of Interest
yeah one of the things that I've noticed
over the years running my workshop
programs and doing presentations at
different science museums is at the
larger metropolitan areas I noticed that
the mix between female and male students
is about 60 40 where a 60 is a 60 male
40 percent female which is rather High
compared to compared to yeah the smaller
areas like the Allentown Lehigh Valley
area where I would have to say the male
participation is about 90 or higher so
you see it you see a larger percentage
of
nine girls in the in the course this
year which was an improvement from last
year right what made them develop this
program what was the Catalyst that got
this program started well it was a
corporation that works
well in Colombia were doing native
technician training here at the career
center and the high schoolers became
extremely interested in what the
um the training what
mom and they started to really bug the
tutors and the
instructors and say you know when can we
play with labels you know when are we
going to be under there and there is
such a need
um nationally for laser technicians that
um really they're there aren't enough
to go around and the earlier that we can
start
to work in the field the better for the
industry generally yes because there are
there is such a need for them
a Indian Health graduate I spoke to
yesterday told me that he'd never had to
look for a job that he'd always been
head hunted and that he'd get
um calls every week from companies
asking him to go to work for for them
that's fantastic that's a wonderful
program that's a wonderful program yeah
let's move on for a minute and we'll get
back to you to close out the show across
let's move on to uh Renee okay and can I
just say that I've got another student
joined us um Zach young oh hello Zach
say something later okay
he's running hi hi Renee how are you I'm
fine first I'd like to find out what was
the initial interest that you had to
take this program in the first place
well
um I joined a thing called battery
scientists during my ninth grade year as
a freshman and what it was is going to
three different places three different
Saturdays and one went to the Career
Centers to like a hologram
and so when I did it it was really
interesting and once I watched the
videos I got really intrigued to do it
so at that point I changed my entire uh
schedule to make maybe in laser learning
through technology what type of a
hologram did you make
um there I made a hologram of a silver
dollar the back of a silver dollar with
my two initials that were of metal they
were little keychain little things at
Each corner
don't try and spend that because I think
that's against the law don't put that in
any pop machines or soda machines did
you have any problems what were some of
the problems that you had in working
with the holography that you could tell
us about
um
we used air tables but for a laser in
the class we use sand tables and I
didn't know that they would move more
and so I had movement in my I hologram
because my plate was not firm enough in
the plate holder and so it left left
some black splotches on my Holograms but
that's a learning process you learned
something from that right yeah so you
think holography is pretty neat right
yes it's very interesting any future
plans that you'd like to share with us
on where you picture yourself being and
say maybe five years or maybe even
looking far ahead into the future 10
years
um well I plan on going to college and
I'm not sure if I'm going to do a
two-year college for this technology or
if I'm going to go to a four-year
College because
um I want to play softball but I also
want to be a um a laser technician so
I'm not sure what I'm going to do there
but I'm really planning on being a laser
technician and work with Holograms a lot
fantastic well I wish you a lot of luck
thank you can we move on to Mike Walker
yes all right Mike UF photonics 2
student is that correct uh photonics too
yes and I imagine you're working with
some Advanced Techniques such as
non-destructive testing as well actually
that's what my semester paper is going
to be on what type of holograms have you
made so far in the program in the
program I've made split beam Wildlife
reflection splitting transmission and
single white light reflection
there's an excellent page from Norway
that two Norway holographers have put up
obviously if it's in Norway it's Norway
holographers excellent page on single
beam holography and different techniques
that they've worked out over there so if
you get a chance to log on to my website
to listen to this show go to the link
page and you'll see a link for that site
in Norway and you'll see some very
interesting single beam setups where you
can take the single beam used part of it
for the plate and also part of it for
the object beam as well where do you
plan on going with the education that
you're receiving in this program right
after high school I'm gonna take a break
I'm gonna go to a Christian college for
a year get a one-year bottle of
knowledge certificate and I'm gonna go
up north to Indian Hills where I plan to
go and pick the associates three that
they offer and you eventually want to
work as a laser technician yes okay
working with the bigger lasers I imagine
or working with the smaller
there you go that's what you need to do
take whatever comes down the pike that's
for sure
project because it's it's some rather
fascinating yeah why don't you tell us
about that well I'm testing carabiners
which are used for in rock climbing some
high angle Paving and some rescue work
and I'm testing them to determine that
this goal point on the Carabiner on
world will break oh yes and also if
there's a designated Breaking Point as
in weight that I can predict
using interferometry yes and then also
as a side note I'm hoping to be able to
determine if there's a given parameter
if the Carabiner testing exceeds it if
the Carabiner should be retired or if it
should stay in service yes well I have
another question for you why don't you
tell the listeners a little bit about
what an interferometer is and how it's
set up and how you do the process well
um I started out with a single beam
white light reflection hologram setup
and I calculated the exposure time and I
cut the first time in half and I exposed
the plate for that half time okay and
then I blocked the beam and I changed
the object by putting a few grams of
stress on it okay and I finished up the
exposure Tom and I developed power game
and it gave me a horizontal interference
banding because it was stretched along
the vertical axis yes that seems like a
very simple process to do and would you
recommend that as a process for other
students out there if they happen to
have their own home studio as well uh
yeah they had the testing equipment
available yeah okay what sounds very
interesting Michael I want to wish a lot
of luck thank you anything else you want
to add before you go just that the
instructors have pressed safety as the
number one concern in the class
laser here so um
he knows about safety bro I want to get
back to you with a question I move a
little bit closer to the phone okay how
do you deal with the chemistry as far as
safety
um chemistry supplied by TJ
Lake Forest College and he provides um
down that is still safe for our company
called into grass yes
I'm and I I'd like to do some research
into this but I'm not particularly
comfortable with some Flushing
flashing it down the um down the system
so if anybody's out there is looking for
more ecologically sound ways to to deal
with that I would be very
very into finding out
yes because I I imagine I haven't come
across any chemistry yet in holography
or photography that wasn't toxic right
you know I mean there are some chemicals
that are a little bit
yep
come to school today so that's what
we're using but yeah it is a it's an
issue I remember working many many years
ago with Mercure chloride for bleach and
parabenzoquinone and some of those other
things and it's gotten a lot better but
it's uh it's still a concern for many
Educators out there when they have
students in the dark room mixing and
working with the chemistry so I just
wanted to get some of your feedback one
concern is that we do things
have sulfur allergies and these students
put on gloves and
um
yes
because you can get very nasty rashes if
you're a personality disulfur yeah
so yeah it's it's um
long going
also spending more
more chemistry
you know like I said I've been very
welcome to hear any suggestions for
you know alternatives to flash
yeah yeah now you have Zach young with
you yeah I can't just walked through the
door a few minutes ago
[Music]
say hello hello Zach just make sure that
you come up close to the phone and speak
loudly and clearly which I instructed
everyone to do before you were there so
I'll repeat those instructions now for
you okay why don't you tell us uh what
grade you're in to start off because I
don't think we had an introduction of
you in the beginning well I'm in 10th
Grade okay what made you decide to get
involved with this holography program
um my dad he kind of um wanted me to
take it and I thought it would be fun so
that's why I decided to do it
huh oh his dad is okay are you a chip
off the old block I guess so okay what
are some of your future plans what do
you hope to get out of the program
sure yet but I hope to find out soon
okay what have you gotten out of the
program so far well I like it a lot and
I think it's very fun what did you make
a hologram of
um I made a hologram of a necklace that
had it was a dragon
pewter is that what it was
um I think so yeah pewter works really
well with holography for some reason do
you ever notice that yeah it's not it's
not the brightest material
yeah
Star Wars was really hot this year it
died out quick though yeah and
everything on the Shelf died out with it
you know there's so much stuff left on
the Shelf discounted Pearl I I want to
get a little information from you about
uh your changeover and your interest
your recent interest in
laser diodes
yeah well I was fascinated to find out
that you could make Holograms with laser
pointers I'd been everybody been asking
that for ages yeah just being told that
no they're um
um you know unsuitable for making
Holograms coherence
not good
multi-mode problems and and then then
I heard that no problem you know people
of stuff is making Holograms with them
and in terms of Education that is just
going to
give them to what science teachers can
do in the classroom to introduce
students to Life Theory
and I mean when I when I started making
Holograms um
that my parents garage when I was
a pencil lessons right
um it would have been so much easier for
me if I just only had to purchase a
laser pointer rather than egg borrow and
steal equipment
colleges in order to try and make them
so I think they're going to
um it's just gonna it's making its
holography so much more accessible I
think it's
fantastic it's a great discovery in them
I'm so pleased with the people who've
been working on it
I've come up with that have you seen
Jeff blyth's new paper on making your
own holographic plates
um no I haven't but I um
one of my teachers at the Royal College
of Art and he just started to develop
those
um plates while I was there yeah and I
never got a chance to shoot um
emotional complaints I'm gonna
um I haven't yet checked up the
latest information
will do so I'm going to try and get
working on making their own place Baby
by the end of the year yeah if you can
make it to my site by the end of the
week I have the actual published paper
and the worksheet there as well so now
we have lasers that you can buy for ten
dollars
and make your own plates
because everything else I once once we
had the laser diodes everything else was
pretty much inexpensive except for the
recording materials yeah
yeah
what I'd like to see now is
um
once the students are done we work on
sort of two and a half by two and a half
inch plates which luckily into Grassland
now selling in small boxes which makes
it
um affordable again yeah
um you know we want to make large
Holograms there and we we haven't we
haven't got any bigger than
[Laughter]
do there is a possibility
um across that we're going to be getting
past later in here at foreign
[Laughter]
table with a laser pointer on it
someone whispering
I hear somebody whispering in the left
ear of my headphones
we're talking about the Newport cable oh
okay how about if we go around the room
one time and uh let's Renee are you
still there yeah yeah what I'd like to
ask you one more time you thought you
were finished didn't you no what I'd
like to do is ask you to maybe give some
advice to other students who are out
there and particularly female students
who may be interested in getting
involved in the field of high technology
and lasers they may be in school they
may go out and see a hologram and find
it fascinating any advice or tips that
you would give to them one thing about
being a girl in the class is that
you really don't people would think they
get harassed and stuff and you really
don't the guys usually you know they
just kind of treat you like they're one
of them and you just have fun with it
and get to know the get to know everyone
in the class so you're happy
you know with being in that class and no
one really bugs you about it or anything
because I have other two other girls in
my class and we're fine we we stick
together a lot of times so it's it's
really fun and interesting so if you're
a girl and you're just thinking oh gosh
those no girls in there it's real easy
to get along with guys so it's all right
that's
I have three daughters myself so I get
concerned on those issues as well my
oldest daughters
physics major and she finds herself
pretty much in a male dominated
environment quite a few times so what we
try and do is have the girls
at least once or something so that they
can talk about anything that they want
to talk about they've got each other's
email addresses
um we set about six different schools
here so the
same school
when they contact each other and we talk
about any issues that might come up with
relation to
um
um in a non-traditional
environment but at the end of the day
the new technologies are great places to
get jobs that
are paid
and come to traditional women's jobs and
at the end of the day you know working
at what you want to do and being well
paid is
um
if there was anybody could do your
program seems like a very well-balanced
program because you stress art as well
as technology don't you yeah try to I
don't know about my background yeah
info is is we try to make it as creative
as possible
and although we we do serve students
with
students with science interests and and
arts interests it's useful for
the scientists and the artists learn a
lot from each other I think in terms of
different solving and just general ways
of thinking yes if they're not too
diverse a group at this age either you
know people there are lots of people who
are interested in
as well as
appliances and you're building skills
that are very valuable for later in life
because they will have to deal with
people with all types of interests and
things of that nature when they're out
in the workforce as well
and and all different ways of thinking
are equally valuable yes Mike yes any
final comments what you'd like to throw
out there to perhaps another student who
may be sitting in his bedroom listening
to this show right now thinking lasers
are really cool well if you can find
somebody to help guide you pursue it
Zach how about you I feel the same way
okay do any of you three Renee Zach or
Mike feel that you would be able to
leave this program and go out and just
start doing this on your own
sort of a trick question I don't know
that much about it I just know about
holography so if someone asked me about
a single beam I'd be okay there I could
I could teach someone that because I had
to help a lot of the times with the
developing and stuff in class done it
before but if there's anything else I
probably wouldn't I have I've only been
in it from the beginning of this year so
I'm coming up
no way
I would prefer to have more education
but I feel that I could probably hold my
own if I was asked yeah bro any closing
comments or anything you'd like to add
maybe there's something that you would
like to talk about that I didn't touch
on before we go
um no just I would encourage I would
encourage girls out there to look look
at the fields of later working with
lasers and also just to say a
thank you to you I think you'll we
really enjoy looking at your website
with some great sources information and
we thoroughly appreciate that and thank
you for calling us today sure thank you
thank you all for being on the show
it's gonna be a great show and I hope
it's an inspiration to students
everywhere to come on and listen to you
talk about your involvement with the
program and oh it's a wonderful program
I've been doing programs for more years
than I care to remember and I think
yours is very unique and it really is
providing a valuable service and it
shows the holography community in a very
positive light thank you very much
you're welcome take care everybody
bye-bye